Finding Aid for William T. Gossett papers, 1927-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William T. Gossett papers 1927-1987, 1947-1981
Gossett, William T.
19 linear feet
85172 Aa 2
Lawyer with the Bendix Corporation and the Ford Motor Company, and member of numerous legal and public service organizations. Speeches, articles and public statements; material relating to his activities with the American Bar Association, the National Legal Aid and Defender Association, and other legal groups; some files concern his interest in such topics as business ethics, campus government and student dissent in the 1960s, electoral college reform, and legal education; there is also material detailing his involvement in public service organizations concerned largely with civil rights and education; also contracts, agreements, and other documentation relating to reorganization of Wesco Corporation (later National Theatres Corporation), 1933-1936; and reorganization of Fox Film Corporation and Twentieth Century Pictures, July-August 1935.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of this collection was received in 1981 from William T. Gossett (Donor No. 5491 ). Additional material was received in 1997.
The collection is open to research.
William T. Gossett was a nationally known lawyer whose legal, business, and philanthropic efforts spanned more than fifty years of professional and public service. Gossett was born in Gainesville, Texas on September 9, 1904 and spent his youth in Chickasha, Oklahoma. He attended Coe College (Cedar Rapids, Iowa), the University of Utah (A.B., 1925), and Columbia University (LL.B., 1928).
Gossett married Elizabeth Evans Hughes, daughter of Supreme Court Justice Charles Evans Hughes, in 1930. He practiced law in New York for eighteen years, from 1929 to 1947, including service with Bendix Corporation as General Counsel (1945-1947) and Director (1946-1947). Gossett joined Ford Motor Company in 1947 and served as General Counsel, Vice President, Director, and Member of the Executive Committee from 1947 to 1962. He resigned in 1962 to devote more of his time to government and public service. Gossett served as counsel to the Detroit law firm of Dykema, Wheat, Spencer, Goodnow, and Trigg (1964-1970) and as partner in the firm of Dykema, Gossett, Spencer, Goodnow, and Trigg (1970-1977).
William T. Gossett held several important positions within the legal fraternity. He served as President of the American Bar Association (ABA) from 1968 to 1969, was a member of its House of Delegates, and participated in many ABA committees. Gossett was also President of the American Bar Foundation (1964-1966), Secretary (1958-1960), and Chairman (1960-1962) of the Fellows of the American Bar Foundation, Director and President of the National Legal Aid and Defender Association (1961-1964), Director (1961-1965) of the American Judicature Society, Director of the Council on Legal Education in Professional Responsibility, Director and co-organizer of the Council on Legal Education Opportunity (1968-1969), Director of the Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, and a member of the Institute for Judicial Administration --American Bar Association Joint Commission on Juvenile Justice Standards.
Public service concerns included appointment as Deputy Special Representative for Trade Negotiations, with the rank of Ambassador (1962-1963), membership on the Federal Commission on Executive, Legislative, and Judicial Salaries (1968-1969; 1973), the National Advisory Committee on the Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) Legal Services Program (1967-1973), and the Michigan Civil Rights Commission (1964-1966). Gossett served on the board of trustees of many educational institutions: Atlanta University, Columbia University, Morehouse College, and the Cranbrook Foundation. Interests in the Michigan area included Harper-Grace Hospitals, the Metropolitan Detroit Council of Churches, New Detroit, Inc, the Economic Club of Detroit, and the Detroit Symphony Orchestra. Gossett was honored by the American Jewish Congress, the National Conference of Christians and Jews, the Detroit Council of Churches and many colleges and universities for his humanitarian efforts.
Gossett also served as the Chairman of the National Board of the United Negro College Fund, Inc. (1961-1967), Trustee (1935-1947) and President (1946-1947) of the Riverside Church in New York City, and as a member of the National Advisory Council for the University of Utah. Private business interests led him to serve as the Director of Dart Industries, Inc. and the One William Street Fund, Inc. Gossett was on the Executive Committee and held the position of Chairman Emeritus with Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation. He also was a founding member of the Board of Directors of the American President's Life Insurance Company (1965-1967).
William T. Gossett died July 20, 1998.
The William T. Gossett collection chronicle his professional career as a lawyer and businessman as well as those many public service activities in which he was active. The collection was received in two accessions, 1981 and 1997. The 1981 accession, the largest of the two, consisted of the following series: Vita; Speeches, Articles, and Statements; Professional Activities; Topical Files; Public Service Files; Hospitals and Organizations; Colleges Universities, and Schools; and Personal Correspondence. The smaller 1997 accession included these series: Biographical and Personal Materials; Speeches, Articles, and Statements; Photographs; and Twentieth Century-Fox. There was some slight overlap in the content of the two accessions, particularly in Gossett's speeches and articles. No attempt was made, however, to intersperse this similar material.
Subjects:
American Bar Association.; Bendix Corporation.; Business ethics.; Civil rights--United States.; Ford Motor Company.; Gossett, William T.; Law.; Lawyers--Michigan.; National Legal Aid and Defender Association.; Elections--United States.; Student movements--United States.; Twentieth Century Pictures.; Fox Film Corporation.; Motion picture industry--United States.; Wesco Corporation.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Community service.; Education.; Gossett, Elizabeth.; Gossett, William T.; Hughes family.; Oakland University.; United Negro College Fund.; Women.
Contributors:
Gossett, Elizabeth.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Postcards.
- Biographical
  - Vita (Box 1)
    (1-1)
- Speeches, Articles, and Statements 1947-1981
  The Speeches, Articles, and Statements series includes 230 of Gossett's compositions. This material expresses Gossett's views on a great many topics of both legal and personal interest to him. Gossett spoke frequently on such matters as: the role of the lawyer in the corporate structure, human rights, equal justice, religion, corporate responsibility, "mobbism," electoral college reform, crime and violence, and legal aid for the poor.
  - "Partners in Freedom," Association of Governing Boards of State Universities and Allied Institutions and the Faculty of the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor October 2, 1947 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-2)
  - "The Law Belongs to You," Alumni Homecoming Convocation of Coe College, Cedar Rapids, Iowa October 31, 1947 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-3)
  - "Labor Law and Christian Ethics," Men's Class of the Riverside Church, New York City, New York February 24, 1948 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-4)
  - [Untitled Speech], Highland Park Thirty-Five Year Employees Dinner, Dearborn, Michigan December 14, 1948 (Outline, drafts, and final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-5)
  - "Cranbrook School Commencement Address," 1948 [Outline] (Box 1)
    (1-6)
  - "Unionization of Foremen at Ford Motor Company," Testimony before the Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, Washington D.C. February 16, 1949 (Printed copy and background material) (Box 1)
    (1-7; 1-8)
  - "General Counsel's Office," Management Meeting of Ford Motor Company, Dearborn, Michigan April 20, 1949 (final copy and printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-9)
  - [Untitled Speech], 6th Conference of Inter-American Bar Association, Dearborn, Michigan May 24, 1949 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-10)
  - "Big Labor in the Democratic Society," Annual Meeting of the Chicago Bar Association, Chicago, Illinois June 15, 1950 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-11)
  - "Highways and Horizons," Society of Automotive Engineers, Los Angeles, California August 15, 1950 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-12)
  - "Nobody wants to be Sam," [Undelivered speech] September, 1951 (Drafts and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-13)
  - "Justice and TV," International Association of Industrial Accident Boards and Commissions, Dearborn, Michigan October 1, 1951 (Printed copy and background information) (Box 1)
    (1-14;1-15)
  - "Which Road to Brotherhood?" National Conference of Christians and Jews, Fort Worth, Texas April 17, 1952 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-16)
  - "A Call to Leadership," Southwestern Legal Foundation, Dallas, Texas April 18, 1952 (Printed copy, drafts, correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-17)
  - "A Call to Leadership," Men's Association of the Third Presbyterian Church, Rochester, New York May 27, 1952 (Draft copy) (Box 1)
    (1-18)
  - "A Call to Leadership," Detroit Bar Association, Detroit, Michigan June 4, 1952 (final copy; and printed copy, published as "Are We Neglecting Constitutional Liberty?, ABA Journal, Vol. 38, October, 1952) (Box 1)
    (1-19)
  - "Cranbrook 'Moving Up' Ceremony," June 6, 1952 (Outline) (Box 1)
    (1-20)
  - "Human Rights and the American Bar," Michigan Judges Association, Dearborn, Michigan September 4, 1952 (final copy, printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-21)
  - "Liberty Imperilled," Detroit News (Guest Editorial), February 20, 1953 (Printed copy and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-22)
  - [Untitled Speech] 1953 United Negro College Fund Dinner, Detroit, Michigan, April 20, 1953 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-23)
  - [Untitled Speech], Ford Motor Company Scholarship Awards Banquet, Dearborn, Michigan June 30, 1953 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-24)
  - "Access to Justice: The True Significance of Legal Aid," Legal Aid-Lawyer Referral Service Luncheon, Boston, Massachusetts August 25, 1953 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-25)
  - "Freedom and Imagination," Annual Convention of Beta Theta Pi Fraternity, Pasadena, California September 4, 1953 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-26)
  - "The Law and Group Ethics," Quadrangle Club of the University of Chicago Law School, Chicago, Illinois November 10, 1953 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-27)
  - [Untitled Speech], Symposium on Legislative Investigation, College of Law, University of Notre Dame, South Bend, Indiana December 9, 1953 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-28)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches and Correspondence 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    (1-29)
  - [Untitled Speech], Michigan Association of School Administrators, Detroit, Michigan January 22, 1954 (final copy and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-30)
  - [Untitled Speech], Centennial Senior Day Convocation of Western College, Oxford, Ohio February 23, 1954 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-31)
  - [Untitled Speech], Municipal Judges Association, Dearborn, Michigan April 10, 1954 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-32)
  - "The Right to be Wrong," Washington and Lee University, Lexington, Virginia April 16, 1954 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-33)
  - [Untitled Speech], Ann Arbor Chapter, National Conference of Christians and Jews, Ann Arbor, Michigan May 18, 1954 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-34)
  - [Untitled Speech], Wisconsin Region National Conference of Christians and Jews, Milwaukee, Wisconsin May 27, 1954 (Printed copy) (Box 1)
    (1-35)
  - [Untitled Speech], Thirty-Third Annual Legal Aid Conference, Rochester, New York October 13, 1955 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-36)
  - [Acceptance Speech], Eighth Annual Amity Award Luncheon, Detroit Women's Division of the American Jewish Congress, Detroit, Michigan February 16, 1955 (Drafts and clippings) (Box 1)
    (1-37)
  - "The Role of the Corporation Counsel," John Randolph Tucker Lecture, Washington and Lee University May 11-12, 1956 (Printed copy and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-38)
  - [Untitled Speech], Wyandotte County Bar Association, Kansas City, Kansas May 17, 1956 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-39)
  - "Ford as a Publicly Owned Corporation," Ford Motor Company Management Conference, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia June 16, 1956 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-40)
  - [Welcoming Statement], Annual Meeting, American Bar Association, Dallas, Texas August 27, 1956 (final copy) (Box 1)
    (1-41)
  - "Corporate Citizenship-The Role of the Corporation Counsel," Cincinnati Bar Association, Cincinnati, Ohio December 17, 1956 (Drafts and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-42)
  - [Other John Randolph Tucker Lectures, 1956] (Box 1)
    (1-43)
  - Management in a Free Society," Synagogue Adult Institute, Detroit, Michigan March 12, 1957 (Draft and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-44)
  - [Untitled Speech], Dinner given by the Council of the Bar of England for the House of Delegates of the American Bar Association July 24, 1957 [Drafts] (Box 1)
    (1-45)
  - "Equal Justice for All," Michigan State Bar Journal, May, 1975 vol. 36 (Printed copy and correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-46)
  - [Acceptance Speech], Probus Club Award Dinner, Detroit, Michigan February 15, 1958 [Drafts] (Box 1)
    (1-47)
  - "A Tribute to Noel Thomas Dowling," Columbia Law Review, vol. 58, May, 1958 [Drafts] (Box 1)
    (1-48)
  - "The Administrative Process: Comment on Warner W. Gardner's Papers," Columbia Law School Centennial Conference, Columbia University, New York City, New York November 6-8, 1958 [Drafts and background materials, correspondence] (Box 1)
    (1-49; 1-50; 1-51)
  - "Buttress of Our Conscience," Annual Brotherhood Dinner of the Detroit Round Table, National Conference of Christians and Jews Detroit, Michigan November 20, 1958 (Printed copy and drafts, clippings, correspondence) (Box 1)
    (1-52; 1-53; 1-54)
  - "People Without Lawyers," This Week, 1958 (Draft copy) (Box 1)
    (1-55)
  - "What My Religion Means to Me," Detroit Free Press, February 11, 1959 (Printed copy, correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-1)
  - "Salute to the Toledo Bar," Toledo Legal Aid Society, Toledo, Ohio February 19, 1959 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-2)
  - "Labor Law and Group Ethics," Church-Industry Group, Kirk-in-the-Hills Church, Bloomfield Hills, Michigan April 20, 1959 (Printed copy, correspondence, clippings) (Box 2)
    (2-3; 2-4; 2-5)
  - "The Role of the Corporation in Public Affairs: I. The Reality and the Opportunity," Committee on Corporate Law Departments, American Bar Association, Miami Beach, Florida August 25, 1959 (Printed copy) (Box 2)
    (2-6)
  - "Balancing Power in the Collective Bargaining," Columbia Law School News, October, 1959 (Detroit News, October 8, 1959) (Printed copy) (Box 2)
    (2-7)
  - "Corporation Counsel and Social Responsibility," Junior Bar Section of Michigan State Bar, Detroit, Michigan November 19, 1959 (Printed Copies and final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-8)
  - "Ford's Fiftieth Anniversary in Texas," Dallas Community Relations Committee Dinner, Dallas, Texas December 17, 1959 [Drafts and correspondence] (Box 2)
    (2-9)
  - [Untitled Speech], National Conference of Christians and Jews Citation Dinner, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma January 28, 1960 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-10)
  - [Introductory Remarks], For Attorney General William P. Rogers, Detroit Economic Club, Detroit, Michigan February 8, 1960 (final copy and Roger's speech correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-11)
  - "Acceptance of Chairmanship of the Fellows of the American Bar Foundation," A.B.A. Mid-Year Meeting, Chicago, Illinois February 21, 1960 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-12)
  - "Looking Ahead," Chickasha Chamber of Commerce, Chickasha, Oklahoma March 31, 1960 [Drafts] (Box 2)
    (2-13)
  - "Memorial to Boris M. Joffe," Jewish Community Council of Metropolitan Detroit, Detroit, Michigan June 29, 1960 (final copy and correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-14)
  - "Should the House of Delegates of the American Bar Association Reverse Its Position on the Connally Amendment?" American Bar Association, Washington D.C. August 31, 1960 (final copy and correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-15)
  - [Remarks as Master of Ceremonies], John C. Dancy Testimonial Dinner, Detroit, Michigan September 30, 1960 [Draft, miscellaneous material, correspondence] (Box 2)
    (2-16; 2-17)
  - "Distribution in the Legal Climate of the Future, " Ford Motor Company Greenbrier Management Conference, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia November 20, 1960 [Draft and miscellaneous material] (Box 2)
    (2-18)
  - [Untitled Speech], Jane Addams Centennial Luncheon, Detroit, Michigan December 3, 1960 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-19)
  - [Untitled Speech], Presentation of American Bar Association Traffic Court Program Award to Judge George T. Martin, Dearborn, Michigan January 11, 1961 [Drafts, clippings] (Box 2)
    (2-20)
  - "Opening Statement," Oakland County Lincoln Republican Club, 71st Annual Banquet, Farmington, Michigan February 9, 1961 [Draft and printed material] (Box 2)
    (2-21)
  - "The Defense of an Old Frontier: The Foundation's Research Program," Fifth Annual Meeting of the Fellows of the American Bar Foundation, Chicago, Illinois February 19, 1961 (Printed copy, draft, miscellaneous material) (Box 2)
    (2-22)
  - [Untitled Speech], Cornell Law Quarterly Banquet, Ithaca, New York April 14, 1961 [Draft and correspondence] (Box 2)
    (2-23)
  - "Corporate Conscience and Sensitivity," Conference of Federal Judges of the Sixth Circuit, Dearborn, Michigan April 29, 1961 (Printed copy and correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-24)
  - "Born to Action," University of Utah Baccalaureate Address June 4, 1961 (Printed copy and miscellaneous material) (Box 2)
    (2-25)
  - "The Position of the Corporation in Society," Ford Engineering Forum, Dearborn, Michigan June 20, 1961 [Draft and correspondence] (Box 2)
    (2-26)
  - [Remarks], Conference of Chief Justices Dinner, Pasadena, California August 22, 1961 [Draft] (Box 2)
    (2-27)
  - [Untitled Speech], National Catholic Conference for Interracial Justice, Detroit, Michigan August 26, 1961 [Draft] (Box 2)
    (2-28)
  - "Are You Part of the Problem or Part of the Answer," Legal Aid Society, Norfolk, Virginia February 1, 1962 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-29)
  - [Untitled Speech], Tenth Annual University of Texas Law Day, Austin, Texas April 6, 1962 (final copy and printed material) (Box 2)
    (2-30)
  - [Untitled Speech], District XI Conclave of the Phi Alpha Delta Law Fraternity, Detroit, Michigan, Apri1 14 1962 (final copy and printed material) (Box 2)
    (2-31)
  - "Make the Most of It," Kingswood School, Cranbrook, Bloomfield Hills, Michigan June 9, 1962 (final copy, printed material, and correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-32)
  - [Remarks], National Legal Aid and Defender Association Annual Dinner, San Francisco, California August 2, 1962 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-33)
  - [Untitled Speech], Columbia Alumni Luncheon, San Francisco, California August 8, 1962 [Drafts] (Box 2)
    (2-34)
  - [Untitled Speech], Michigan State Bar Meeting Luncheon, Lansing, Michigan September 27, 1962 (final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-35)
  - "Making Paper Rights Worth Something," American Bar Association Journal 1962 [Draft and correspondence] (Box 2)
    (2-36)
  - "The Kennedy Round and the Common Market," Dinner Meeting of the George Washington University European Common Market Conference, Washington D.C. April 9, 1963 (Box 2)
    (2-37)
  - "To the Detriment of None," Second Annual Forum on the Major Trends and Problems of Today's World, Oakland University, Rochester, Michigan April 29, 1963 (Box 2)
    (2-38)
  - 'The Kennedy Round-Progress and Promise, " Koppers Company-Business International Round Table, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania July 17, 1963 [Correspondence, drafts, miscellaneous material] (Box 2)
    (2-39)
  - "Introduction of Christian A. Herter," Detroit Economic Club, Detroit, Michigan March 30, 1964 (Correspondence, final copy) (Box 2)
    (2-40)
  - [Untitled Speech], Presentation of Charles Evan Hughes Award to Dr. Robert J. McCracken, The Men's Class of Riverside Church, New York, New York March 31, 1964 [Correspondence, final copy, printed material] (Box 2)
    (2-41)
  - [Summary statements], Metropolitan Detroit Conference on Religion and Race, Detroit, Michigan April 12, 1964 [Correspondence, printed material] (Box 2)
    (2-42)
  - [Letter to Roger Baldwin], 49th Anniversary Dinner of the American Civil Liberties Union, Detroit, Michigan May 9, 1964 [Drafts, printed material] (Box 2)
    (2-43)
  - [Untitled Speech], Association of General Counsel, Point Clear, Alabama May 17, 1964 (Box 2)
    (2-44)
  - "Tribute to Charles G. Mortimer," Harvard Club, New York City, New York June 3, 1964 (Box 2)
    (2-45)
  - "Introduction of Lady Reading," American Bar Association Annual Meeting, Third Assembly, New York City, New York August 13, 1964 (Box 2)
    (2-46)
  - "The Plight of the Needy," National Legal Aid and Defender Association, Buffalo, New York September, 1964 (Printed material and other remarks) (Box 2)
    (2-47)
  - "Are You Part of the Problem or a Part of the Answer?" Grosse Pointe Human Relations Council, Grosse Pointe, Michigan December 3, 1964 (Box 2)
    (2-48)
  - "Introduction of the Reverend Dr. A. Dale Fiers," Metropolitan Detroit Council of Churches Annual Meeting, Royal Oak, Michigan January 22, 1965 [Draft and printed material] (Box 2)
    (2-49)
  - [Panel Discussion-"Assigned Counsel V. Public Defender,"] Lansing, Michigan February 20, 1965 [Correspondence and printed material] (Box 2)
    (2-50)
  - [Remarks and Introduction of Honorable John T. Connor], United Negro College Fund Convocation, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania April 5, 1965 [Correspondence and miscellaneous material] (Box 2)
    (2-51)
  - "E. Blythe Stason," American Bar Foundation Annual Meeting, New Orleans, Louisiana June 7, 1965 (Box 2)
    (2-52)
  - "Getting the Most Out of Life," Kalamazoo College Commencement, Kalamazoo, Michigan June 13, 1965 [Drafts, correspondence] (Box 2)
    (2-53)
  - "Social Responsibilities of Corporation Counsel," Fourth Annual Corporate Counsel Institute, Northwestern University School of Law, Chicago, Illinois October 14-15, 1965 (Box 2)
    (2-54)
  - "Buttresses of Our Conscience," Brotherhood Citation Dinner of the National Conference of Christians and Jews, Denver, Colorado December 2, 1965 (Box 2)
    (2-55)
  - "The Law: Leader or Laggard in Our Society," American Bar Association Journal, December, 1965 [Drafts, printed copy) (Box 2)
    (2-56)
  - [Untitled Speech], Presenting Amity Award of the Detroit Women's Division of the American Jewish Congress to Judge Wade H. McCree, Jr., Detroit, Michigan March 9, 1966 (Box 2)
    (2-57)
  - [Untitled Speech], Columbia (University) in Detroit, Detroit, Michigan March 16, 1966 (Box 2)
    (2-58)
  - [Untitled Speech], Dinner honoring A.W. Dent on his Twenty-fifth year as Dillard University President March 17, 1966 [Correspondence, draft] (Box 2)
    (2-59)
  - [Symposium], United Negro College Fund Convocation, Washington D.C. March 28, 1966 (Printed material, correspondence) (Box 2)
    (2-60)
  - [Honorary Degree Award], Tuskegee Institute, Tuskegee, Alabama April 3, 1966 (Printed material and clipping) (Box 2)
    (2-61)
  - [Missing Speech], Practicing Law Institute, New York City, New York June 20-21, 1966 (Printed material) (Box 2)
    (2-62)
  - [Untitled Speech], Alumni Planning Conference on Columbia University Development, New York City, New York June 29, 1966 [Correspondence and draft] (Box 2)
    (2-63)
  - "Legislative Redistricting by Non-Legislative Agencies," National Municipal League, Boston, Massachusetts November 14, 1966 (Box 2)
    (2-64)